<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mercy rejoycing against judgement: or, God waiting to be gracious to a sinfull nation. A sermon preached before the honorable House of Commons in Margarets Westminster, upon the solemne day of their publique humiliation and monethly fast, Octob. 29. 1645. / By John Strickland, B.D. pastor of the church at Edmonds in the citie of New Sarum, now preacher at Peters Poor, London, and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Strickland, John, 1600 or 1601-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E307_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861152</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E307[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mercy rejoycing against judgement: or, God waiting to be gracious to a sinfull nation. A sermon preached before the honorable House of Commons in Margarets Westminster, upon the solemne day of their publique humiliation and monethly fast, Octob. 29. 1645. / By John Strickland, B.D. pastor of the church at Edmonds in the citie of New Sarum, now preacher at Peters Poor, London, and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Strickland, John, 1600 or 1601-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matth. Simmons, for Henry Overton, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears an order to print on verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXX, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113280:1"/>
            <head>To the honorable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable and worthy Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN you were ſolemnly met before God, to mourn over your ſins, it was my duty to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what I could, the melting of your hearts, that you might <hi>powre them out before the Lord.</hi> I knew not a better ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for ſuch a purpoſe, then to ſet before you, God mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over ſinners, his repentings kindled together, and his bowels turned within him fer them: it cannot but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile upon an ingenuous ſpirit, and make it mourn after the Lord. <hi>Qui nolit impendere amorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Aug.</note> 
               <hi>ſaltem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendat,</hi> ſaith a father.</p>
            <p>And the voyce of <hi>Mercy</hi> (after the windes, and earthquakes, and fires of judgement, that have gone before, and have ſhaken the mountaines, and broken the rocks in pieces) be but a ſtill ſmall voyce, yet it may prevail more then thoſe, if God be in it; and I hope he is: For, if I miſtake not, <hi>Mercy</hi> is the preſent receipt which the great Phyſitian hath preſcribed to make up the cure of ſick <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a Cordiall after blood-letting, and many bitter pills, that have pul'd her down. God is now powring out one mercy after another upon us, and (as I may ſay) rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and working in the oyle of <hi>Mercy,</hi> to take away the ſtiffnes of our hearts and to make them pliable. Now that the language of providence herein, might be both more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate
<pb facs="tcp:113280:2"/> and impreſsive, I have brought the Word, to ſet home upon the heart, Gods own diſpenſations, God makes the doctrine, in preaching <hi>Mercy,</hi> and that in most reall demonſtrations, I have endeavoured to make the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Mercy</hi> unto our hearts, that by may of uſe, it might bring us to repentance, and teach us to <hi>feare the Lord and his goodneſſe.</hi> It ſeems to be a leſſon God would fain have us to learn at this time, I have therefore willingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it unto you from the pulpit, where you heard it with patience. And likewiſe (at your appointment) I now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it unto you and the world from the Preſs, with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that by both or either (hearing or reading) the Spirit of God may bring it in, with a bleſsing, to reach the heart.</p>
            <p>And whereas, when you had ſent up the cry of your ſouls unto God upon the faſting day, I preſented unto your eares the cry of many thouſand ſouls, out of the North, where they cry for food, but there is none to break unto them the bread of life, and you willingly hearkened: give me leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new my motion (as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi>) for the place of my fathers Sepulchers, which lieth waſte. It is a work of ſo high importance and difficulty, that none are worthy to take it hand, but a Parliament, none can bring reliefe (under God) but you, who are the repairers of our breaches, and the reſtorers of paths to dwell in. The noble and worthy Gentlemen of your honorable Committee for ſending Miniſters into the Northern Counties, know, that they have long been in darkneſſe, even when the light of the Goſpel brake forth gloriouſly over all other parts of the Kingdome in former times of reformation; and yet, though that honorable Committee have been zealous and piouſly diligent in the truſt you have committed to them, (whereby they have procured and ſent ſome labourers into
<pb facs="tcp:113280:2"/> the Vineyards of <hi>York,</hi> and <hi>Dureſme,</hi> and <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> as a happy fruit of reformation by this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſome<note n="a" place="margin"> Weſtmorland <hi>&amp;</hi> Cumberland</note> of thoſe deſolate Counties have not ſo much as taſted of your charity in this kind, to reap the fruit of your religious Ordinance, wherein you have worthily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the maintenance of ſome godly Miniſters there.</p>
            <p>The ſcarceneſſe of Miniſters, the remoteneſſe of thoſe parts, the ſmalneſſe of Church-livings there, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall backwardneſse in Miniſters to goe into thoſe cold Countries, are ſome of the chiefe obſtructions. For the firſt, I doubt not but your wiſdoms will find out a better Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote againſt the ſcarcity of Miniſters, then liberty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying (which ſome plead for upon this ground): if the <hi>Ark</hi> be ſhaken, <hi>Uzzah</hi> may not (under that pretence) put forth his hand to hold it. Rather your Parliamentary care, to reduce and reform our Univerſities, to view all publick Schools, whereby children of pregnant capacities, may bee brought up in a way of learning, to incourage the ſtudy of divinity in Colleges, to ſee that Scholars dwel not too long in Fellowſhips when they are fitted for the ſervice of the Church (according to the proviſoes that are made already in the ſtatutes of ſome Colleges in <hi>Oxford</hi>): your wiſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration (I ſay) of theſe and like things, will beget great hopes of a plentifull harveſt (even of labourers) in the next generation. And in the mean time (as to the want of Miniſters in the North) a few bright-ſhining lights well diſpoſed of in thoſe dark places, ſet up (I mean) in the moſt eminent towns of <hi>Weſtmorland</hi> and <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland;</hi> by preaching there, and travelling about, would give great light every one of them ſeverally a great way in the circumjacent Countrey.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond and third impediments, I need not tell
<pb facs="tcp:113280:3"/> you that their maintenance had need to be ſuch as may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Miniſters, againſt remoteneſſe and coldneſſe of the countrey, which may be ſufficiently provided for, if it may pleaſe this honorable Houſe, that the Impropriations which are ſequeſtred, and the ſmall Church-livings in thoſe Counties, be collected and treaſured up in faithfull hands, as one publick ſtock for the maintenance of ſuch as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully labour in the harveſt there. Touching the backward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Miniſters to goe into thoſe Countries, ſince it is God that inclines the hearts of men, it hath been, and is my prayer, that God would ſtir up the hearts of his ſervants to undertake ſo glorious a work, as the planting of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in thoſe barren parts, wherein ſome faithfull Miniſters have in former and later times laboured with abundance of bleſſed ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt reformation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were ſo few, that, many places of the Kingdome were like to be unſuppli d, the Miniſters adviſed the great Councell of that Kingdom, to uſe their authority (with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Church) for the ſending of Miniſters of ability to beſtow their gifts where was moſt need. I preſume not hereby to preſident your godly wiſdomes, but in all that I have ſaid, my deſire is to provoke your zealous and mature conſultations, to find out ſome effectuall way, for the ſetting up of a godly Miniſtery in the <hi>North:</hi> wherein, as alſo in all other your weighty undertakings for the Church or Common-wealth, that the bleſsing of heaven may crowne your unwearied labours, with ſucceſs, hath been, is, and ſhall be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my ſtudy in</hi> Broadſtreet, <date>Nov. <hi>29. 1645.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The meaneſt of them that ſerve you in the Work of the Goſpel.</hi> John Strickland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113280:3"/>
            <head>MERCY REJOYCING <hi>AGAINST</hi> JUDGEMENT: <hi>OR,</hi> God waiting to be gracious to a ſinfull Nation.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH 30.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And therfore will the Lord waite that he may be gracious, and therefore will the Lord be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you: for the Lord is a God of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Bleſſed are all they that waite for him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt the ſinnes of <hi>Judah,</hi> which they committed in the time of the Babyloniſh captivity, after the death of <hi>Gedaliah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ahikam,</hi> whom <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babel</hi> had made Governour over them in <hi>Iudae.</hi> For when as the Lord had promiſed them delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranceat, length, from the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> if in the meane time, they would have ſit ſtil in their own land under the ſaid Governour; and would have provided well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113280:4"/> for their ſecurity, and ſubſiſtence during their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity. <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.10.11.<note place="margin"> Jer. 42.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>If ye will ſtill abide in this Land, then will I build you and not pull you down, and I will plant you, and not pluck you up. Be not afraid of the King of</hi> Babylon <hi>of whom you are afraid, be not afraid of him, ſaith the Lord: for I am with you to ſave you, and to deliver you from his hand.</hi> Yet they, (tranſported with fear, leſt the <hi>Babylonians</hi> ſhould revenge upon them the bloud of <hi>Gedaliah,</hi> whom they had treacherouſly ſlain) diſtruſt Gods promiſe, and will needs <hi>go down into Egypt to ſtrengthen themſelves in the ſtrength of</hi> Pharaoh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſe</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>and to truſt in the ſhadow of Egypt;</hi> ver. 2. which their ſin the Prophet amplifies, with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aggravation. Firſt, That they did carry it cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, <hi>propriis conſilijs addicti,</hi> and in their carnall policie would have covered it, pretending to aske counſell of the Lord, to colour their deſign, when they were altogether reſolved upon their ſinfull courſe.<note place="margin"> Ier. 42.20.</note> So the Prophet tels them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.20. <hi>Ye diſſembled in your hearts when you ſent me to the Lord.</hi> and ſo the Prophet, <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>They take Counſel, but not of mee, they cover with a covering, but not of my Spirit.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they did it rebelliouſly, <hi>For the Lord had cried concerning this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Your ſtrength is to ſit ſtill;</hi> ver. 7. Yet when the prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> effectually laid the Law to them in this point, and admoniſhed them to take notice thereof, ſaying, <hi>The Lord hath ſaid, O ye remnant of Judah, go ye not into</hi> Egypt, <hi>know certainly that I have admoniſhed you this day.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ier 42.19.</note> Ier. 42.19. Notwithſtanding they would <hi>not heare the Law of the Lord</hi> but rather oppoſed it; ſaying <hi>to the Seers, ſee not, and to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Prophecy not unto us right things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 9.10.11.</note> ver. 9.10.11.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113280:4"/> So they ſaid, and worſe unto the Prophet,<note place="margin"> Ier 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>Ier.</hi> 43.2.3. <hi>Thou ſpeakeſt falſly, the Lord our God hath not ſent thee to ſay, Go not down into Egypt to ſojourne there. But</hi> Baruch <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Neriah <hi>ſetteth thee on againſt us, for to deliver us into the hand of the</hi> Chaldeans; <hi>that they might put us to death, and carry us away Captives into</hi> Babylon.</p>
            <p>Againſt this their ſinne thus aggravated, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſets himſelf to Denounce Gods Judgement; wherin he declareth both what the Judgement ſhall be, and how it ſhall be inflicted; the matter of the Judgement is, that God will make the broken reed of <hi>Egypt</hi> wheron they leaned, to go into their hands and pierce them, (as of <hi>Egypt</hi> it is ſaid in another Storie <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.6.) <hi>The ſtrength of</hi> Pharaoh <hi>ſhall be your ſhame,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Iſa. 36.6.</note> 
               <hi>and the truſt in the ſhadow of</hi> Egypt <hi>your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. ver.</hi> 3. And for the manner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</note> the Judgment ſhall befall them unexpectedly and on a ſudden; <hi>as a breach in a high wall at an inſtant,</hi> againſt which there can be made neither reſiſtance nor defence. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. And it ſhall fall upon them heavily in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</note> ſo that they ſhall be broken all to pieces, <hi>like the burſting of a Potters veſſell, that affords not a ſheard to take fire from the hearth, or water out of the pit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 14.</note> And it ſhall fall up-upon them in a way of Retaliation, wherin God will make the ſeverall parts of their ſin to recoile upon them, as ſeverall parts of their Judgement: they make <hi>Egypt</hi> their hope, God will make <hi>Egypt</hi> their ſhame; they would flee from their enemies in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Policie againſt Gods command, they ſhall flee before their enemies for their own neceſſity: they would be ſwift to eſcape their enemies, God will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113280:5"/> make their enemies ſwift to overtake them: they were afraid of the <hi>Babylonians</hi> without cauſe when God would have had them to be fearleſſe; but now they ſhall have cauſe to fear, and flee from their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that ſhall purſue them, <hi>till they be left as a Beacon on the top of a Mountain;</hi> Even as one tree left for a Sea-mark in the cuting down of a Forreſt, <hi>and as an Enſigne on a hill,</hi> or a forſaken Standard when all the men that fought under it are cut off.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 16.17. But while the Lord was going on ſo fiercely to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them, he ſtayes his hand and forbears; theſe rebellious Jewes neare about 150 years, (as <hi>Hierom</hi> computes) between the <hi>denouncing</hi> of this Judgement in <hi>Iſaiahs,</hi> and <hi>in</hi> the execution of it in <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> time. If any wonder why our Prophet gives you an accompt, that God doth it not to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or wink at their wickedneſſe,<note place="margin"> Alvarez in Iſaian.</note> 
               <hi>ſed minatur cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidus non exequendi minas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Alvarez,</hi> he threatnes that he might but threaten, and thereby bring them into a capacity of mercy, that for the preſent were fit only for wrath and Judgement. <hi>And therefore will the Lord waite that he may be gracious,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>My text is a Sermon, wherein the Prophet gives the Jewes an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, why: God did not forthwith deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though they were even ripe for Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin"> Diviſion.</note> In this Sermon we have ſet before us, the juſt lineaments &amp; properties of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Doctrin, <hi>The Lord waites to be gracious.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Reaſons of it 2. <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. He will be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his mercy.</item>
                     <item>2. He is a God of Judgement.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. An application or uſe of the Doctrin; <hi>Bleſſed are all they that waite for him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113280:5"/>
            <p>Here you ſee my Sermon cut out, both in parts and method:<note place="margin"> The words opened.</note> Ere we come to handle the Doctrin (which is the firſt branch) the words thereof are to be explai, ned, &amp; among them <hi>particula <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> non eſt omittenda</hi> ſaith <hi>Forerius,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Therfore]</note> the firſt word [therefore] is to be well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; This Relative and Illative paritcle, bids us look for premiſſes whereon to inferr the text; but the difficulty of finding any hath troubled expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Some do make the inference from the ſin of the people, in refuſing to waite upon the Lord when he called upon them ſaying,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 15.16.</note> v. 15.16. <hi>In returning &amp; reſt ſhall ye be ſaved, in quietnes &amp; confidence ſhal be your ſtrength, and ye would not, but ſaid no;</hi> as if the Prophet ſhould have ſaid, there muſt of neceſſity be a waiting; the viſion is for an appointed time, and ſeeing you will not waite upon, and be obedient to him, behold (and be aſtoniſhed) <hi>Therfore the Lord will waite that he may be gracious unto you:</hi> This inference holds out the freeneſſe and riches of divine goodneſſe, becauſe God is gracious, therefore he will waite that he may be gracious. Some do make the inference from the Judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t denounced againſt the ſin of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that ſince God had determined to bring evill upon them if they repented not, (for every threatning carries in it a tacite condition of impenitency) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore till the time that the Decree bring forth, <hi>The Lord will waite that he may be gracious unto you.</hi> And this holds out the riches and bountifulneſſe of his patience and longſufferance-ſpoken of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. But I humbly conceive with others that the word [therefore] looks beſt inward into the text it ſelfe, where we find the exaltation and glory of his grace
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113280:6"/> and mercy, the ſpring and (as I may ſay) the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of God to waite, and the finall cauſe of this his waiting; he will waite that he may be gracious, and he will waite that he may be exalted in ſhowing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: and this Gods own deſign of advancing his goodneſſe and patience, towards theſe obſtinate and ſinfull <hi>Iewes,</hi> offers the faireſt and moſt genuine ground of inference: <hi>And therefore will the Lord wait that he may be gracious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Waite] <hi>expectabit,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Waite]</note> which ſignifies <hi>locum paenitendo concedere:</hi> others tell us that this doth not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſe the force of the Originall word, which ſignifies as much as a longing expectation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter expecta vit</note> 
               <hi>in hiare vel anhelare,</hi> as a hungry man waits for meat, or as a theef doth waite for a man to rob him. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.9. it may denote <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a looking after with neck ſtretched out, rendred <hi>the earneſt expectation of the creature, waiting for the manifeſtation of the ſons of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Rom. 8.19.</note> Rom. 8.19. the ſumme is, <hi>huc tendit, in hoc totus eſt ut miſereatur,</hi> The Lord waits as being very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be gracious unto you, though the <hi>Iewes</hi> were unfit for mercie, and fit for Judgement at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the Lord in waiting ſuſpends his juſtice, and looks ſot a time that he may be mercifull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That be may be gracious</hi>] He is ſo alwaies in himſelf,<note place="margin"> Gracious]</note> but doth not alwaies appear ſuch unto his people, they are not alwaies capable of the ſweet aſpects of grace, by reaſon that their ſins do ſometimes bind them overto his Juſtice; ſo that he cannot be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>ſalvâ juſtitiâ,</hi> till they repent &amp; return to him; &amp; then he will be (that is, declare himſelf to be) graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unto you, in pardoning your ſin, in taking off
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113280:6"/> your puniſhment, in delivering you from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence gone out againſt you, and in ſetting you at reſt in your own land. <hi>And therfore will the Lord waite, that he may be thus gracious unto you.</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> The point.</p>
            <p>Sometimes God wonderfully ſuſpends his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin"> Doct.</note> and waits upon a provoking people, that he may be mercifull to them.</p>
            <p>What the Poets faine of their <hi>Jupiter,</hi> (that he never throws his Thunder-bolts, but when furies wreſt them out of his hands) in a ſenſe is true indeed of God, he never takes his rod in hand unprovoked, nor alwaies when he is provoked by the ſinnes of a people.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Si quoties peccant homines, ſua fulmina mittat</l>
               <l>Jupiter, exiguo tempore inermis erit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>God is provoked every day,</hi> yet is he ſlow to anger; Yea ſomtimes when he has determined to bring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill upon a people, and put himſelf into a poſture of Judgement, drawn out the ſword, and ſmitten them, though they ceaſe not to provoke him, he ceaſeth to puniſh them; as a tender Father in correcting a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and graceleſs child, holds his hand ſomtime before the child begg for mercie, and of meere grace forbears, ſo God did w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Pſa. 78.38.<note place="margin"> Pſa. 78.38.</note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their diſſembling, with their flattering tongus, &amp; covenant breaking hearts, <hi>He forgave their iniquity and deſtroyed them not, yea many a time turned he his anger away, and would not ſtir up all his wrath;</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Multus in co ſuit ut averte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret iram ſuam <hi>Muſc.</hi>
               </note> The words are, <hi>He multiplyed to turne away his anger;</hi> as they multiplyed to provoke it, he multiplyed to turne it away: and ſo at length overnumbred
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113280:7"/> their ſinnes with his mercies, that they were not deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And when the ſame people of the <hi>Iewes</hi> elſewhere ſeemed to confront Gods Judgements with their obſtinacy, by perſiſting in their ſins, as if they meant to contend with God whether he ſhould prevaile in puniſhing, or they in ſinning: yea when in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (if we look upon it with humane judgement) their puniſhment ſhould have been increaſed, rather then mercy ſhould have been extended to them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how admirably the Lord breaks out into a way of mercy <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.17 18.<note place="margin"> Iſa. 57.17.18.</note> 
               <hi>For the iniquity of his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes was I wroth &amp; ſmote him, I bid me &amp; was wroth, and he went on frowardly in the way of his heart: I have ſeen his waies, and I will heale him: I will lead him alſo and reſtore comforts unto him and to his mourners.</hi> What Logick can draw an argument of mercy from this Topick, <hi>I have ſeene the frowardneſſe of his waies?</hi> Their ſinne was a foul ſin, committed againſt their experience of the evill of ſinne, he had made them taſt of the fruit of their doings; and Gods eye is a pure eye and cannot behold iniquity; ſo that one would have thought God would have concluded, I have ſeen his waies and I will puniſh him; but that he ſhould conclude I have ſeen his waies and I will heale him, is an aſtoniſhment.</p>
            <p>As it was the commendation of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency &amp; ſweet diſpoſition,<note place="margin"> Theodoſius.</note> that it was to him as if he received a benefit, if he might have an opportunity to forgive an injury: So it is the excellency of divine bowels, that the Lord is very deſirous to forgive be cauſe <hi>mercy pleaſeth him;</hi> and will rather ſomtimes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113280:7"/> make an occaſion then want one to take up his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, when it is incenſed againſt his people, &amp; if they be not in themſelves yet, in a capacity of mercy, he will waite til they be, that he may be mercifull to them. It is obſervable upon what ground the Lord ſeems to take up a reſolution, never to deſtroy the world any more by a floud. <hi>Ge.</hi> 8.21.<note place="margin"> Gen. 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>I will not again curſe the ground any more for mans ſake, for the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mans heart is evil from his youth.</hi> He drowned the world before,<note place="margin"> Gen. 6.5.</note> becauſe the imaginations of mans heart were evill; <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. and will he now ſpare it becauſe the imaginations of mans heart are evill?<note place="margin"> Gen. 8.21.</note> what riddle is this? is the evill in mans heart any leſſe then it was? or is it leſſe hatefull in Gods eye then it was? neither ſo nor ſo, but the Lord having now ſmelled a ſweet ſavour in <hi>Noahs</hi> ſacrifice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.21. which was a type of Chriſt, in whom God and man were reconciled; God will now magnifie his mercy and patience, ſo that<note n="*" place="margin"> Multa in ſcriptura effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quae tamen oportet intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Damaſc. lib. 4. de orth. fide cap. 20.</hi> Saepe illa Hebraea particula <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> et graeca <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in bibliis uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur adverſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve pro quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, licet <hi>Tarn. Exer. Bibl in 1 Sam. 2.25.</hi>
               </note> though man be as ſinfull as ever he was, and deſerves that the ground ſhould be curſed again with another floud as well as ever he did; yet God to ſhew the riches of his grace and mercy, <hi>will not again curſe the ground any more for mans ſake, though the imagination of mans heart is evill from his youth;</hi> which leads me to the grounds of reaſon holden out in the next place.</p>
            <p>The reaſons of ſuch Gods wonderfull diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſomtimes, are given in the text; And firſt why he ſuſpends his Judgements ſo unexpectedly and extraordinarily ſomtimes,<note place="margin"> Reaſons</note> when yet a people do ſtill provoke him; even becauſe he will be exalted in his mercy; <hi>And therfore will he be exalted, that he may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113280:8"/> have mercy upon you] exaltabit,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Exalted]</note> ſe he ſhall ſtir up him ſelf that he may have mercy, as intending to ſhow mercy with all his might. When the pſalmiſt would have God help the Church to purpoſe, he intreats the Lord to ſtir up his ſtrength and help her; <hi>Pſa.</hi> 80.2. ſo when he intends here to be mercifull to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he will ſtir up himſelf. Or <hi>exaltabitur parcendo vobis,</hi> God ſhall be exalted in pardoning; it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be <hi>grandis clementia Dei,</hi> (as <hi>Hierom</hi> cals it) when he pardoneth unexſpectedly; he lifts up his mercy above mens thoughts, as far as <hi>the Heavens are above the Earth.</hi> So in the Prophet, God ſpeaks of himſelf, <hi>when he pardoneth aboundantly, Iſa.</hi> 55.7.8.9. I will nor trouble you with the many other inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations that are made of this phraſe, as that it ſignifies the exaltatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods hand, <hi>in fimilitudinem percuſſuri,</hi> as <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> or Gods going up again into Heaven, from whence he was come down out of his place to puniſh them, and the like. The two firſt interpretations give you (as I humbly conceive) the genuine ſenſe and mind of the words, which holds out the reaſon of the point; even that God may be the more exalted, and ſet up in his mercy.</p>
            <p>There is an ordinary courſe or path holden out in Scripture, wherein divine juſtice and mercy, do commonly proceed in puniſhing or in pardoning: When a people ſinne againſt God, they ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; when a people repent of their ſinne, God will repent of their puniſhment, and they ſhall be pardoned, thus it is generally in Gods diſpenſations; and becauſe God hath not tyed or limitted himſelf to walke alwaies (though he hath tyed us alwaies to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113280:8"/> waite upon and expect him) in the way of his word for the diſpenſation of his juſtice and mercy. there is alſo a way of Prerogative (as I may call it) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God may and ſometimes doth diſpenſe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in reſerved caſes, above the common rule,<note place="margin"> Videtur mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcricordiae li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lire, <hi>Theodo. Suepſius.</hi>
               </note> he ſomtimes repents of puniſhing a people, before they repent of ſinning againſt him, as you have heard in the proofe of the point; and when he walks in ſuch untrodden paths, God is ſingularly exalted in his mercy theſe foure waies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin"> How God is exaleed in his mercy by ſuch diſpenſations.</note>Firſt, In the principle of mercy, I mean the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his nature, whereby he is ſo ſtrongly, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly inclin'd to mercy, that he will not retaine anger; he will not be provoked ſomtimes, though he be provoked by the ſins of his people, and this ſets him up ſo incomparable high in the admiration of his people, <hi>Mica.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee; that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſsion of the remnant of his heritage?</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Mica. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>he retaineth not his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for ever, becauſe he delighteth in mercy.</hi> According to what the Lord declared of himſelf to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he made his glory to paſſe before him. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. <hi>The Lord God, mercifull and gracious,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Exod. 24.6.</note> 
               <hi>long ſuffering and aboundant in goodneſſe:</hi> what goodnes is it that God will forbeare to ſtrike in the midſt of provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? The Prophet wholly aſcribes the praiſe of our <hi>non</hi> deſtruction to that, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22. <hi>It is of the Lords mercies that we are not conſumed,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Lam. 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe his compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons faile not.</hi> What goodnes that the great God (on whom all the creatures in Heaven and earth ſhould waite) ſhould waite on his poore creatures!</p>
            <p>Secondly, by ſuch extraordinary diſpenſations
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113280:9"/> God is exalted in the freeneſſe of his mercy: pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing leſſe then we deſerve, is confeſſedly mercy. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9.13.<note place="margin"> Ezr. 9.13.</note> pardoning fully where puniſhment is deſerved is yet more, but how is mercy exalted when bleſſings are given inſtead of puniſhments? I ſay not <hi>praeter meritum,</hi> but <hi>contrameritum?</hi> when there is not only nothing at all in the people to help forward, but almoſt every thing in them that might hinder the exerciſe of mercy; when all the arguments and motives to mercy, muſt be drawn out of Gods own bowels, God muſt needs be very glorious in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it: Thus God held out the gloriouſneſſe of his free mercy toward <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when after their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection he reſtores them, what bleſſings he beſtowes upon them <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.11.<note place="margin"> Ezek. 36.11.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſetle you after your old eſtates, and will do better to you then at the beginning.</hi> The very materials of the bleſſings are large demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of mercy, even that he will do ſuch great things for them; but leſt they ſhould not ſee the full glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his mercy toward them therein, he preſſeth them to take notice that he would do theſe things freely.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 22. <hi>Say unto the houſe of Iſrael, thus ſaith the Lord God, I do not this for your ſakes, O houſe of Iſrael, but for my own holy Names ſake which ye have prophaned among the heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God is hereby exalted in the richneſſe of his mercy: when a people continue in their provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; rebellions againſt God, tis not a little mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that can ſtand in the breach. When <hi>Iſrael Num.</hi> 14.11.12. had very far provoked the Lord,<note place="margin"> num. 14.11.12.</note> ſo that he ſpake of <hi>plaguing &amp; diſinheriting them, Moſes</hi> prays <hi>ver.</hi> 17.19.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 17.19.</note> 
               <hi>That the Lords power may be great</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113280:9"/> and that he will pardon <hi>according to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mercie:</hi> the Lords great wrath was kindled, therefore his power had need be great to keep it in. When a man is thoroughly moved with anger, there is much ado to keep in his paſſion that it break not out; now nothing can be ſo provoking to ſtir up our anger, as ſin is to ſtirre up Gods diſpleaſure againſt a people; how great is that mercy then that can keep in divine wrath? And as he prayed that the power of the Lord might be great, ſo he prayes that his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy may not be little; their great ſinnes will need the <hi>greatneſſe of his mercy.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Eph. 2.4.5.</note> So the Apoſtle <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4.5. when he mentions Gods reconciliation with man, who was by nature a child of wrath, and had nothing to pacifie, but all in him rather to provoke God farther; he preſents <hi>God as rich in mercy</hi> and <hi>of great love,</hi> that could love or think of being reconciled to him <hi>while</hi> yet he was <hi>dead in ſinnes</hi> and treſpaſſes, whereby God may be the more exalted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God is hereby exalted in his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that he doth performe his promiſſes of mercy to his people, even when there lye ſo many and great obſtructions and impediments in his way, by the greatneſſe of his peoples ſinnes, as many times there do. This is the exaltatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſome Expoſitors think is meant in the text,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moller.</hi> in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>ut fides eius in promiſsis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatior fiat apud omnes &amp; illuſtrior,</hi> that God will break through all oppoſition to relieve his people with mercy, when they are under the ſtrongeſt holds of ſin: when he hath entred a Covenant with his people once though they be unfalthfull, 'tis his glory that <hi>hee abideth faithfull,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14.<note place="margin"> 2 Tim. 2.13.</note> if they turn aſide
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113280:10"/> into ſpirituall whoredome and Apoſtaſie (and well enough deſerve a bill of divorce) he will not caſt them off but recover them by repentance, and ſhow mercy unto them, according to his promiſe when he married them unto himſelf,<note place="margin"> Ier. 3.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.14.15. <hi>Turne O backſliding children, ſaith the Lord, for I am married un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and</hi> (though you have broken Covenant with me, I will make good my promiſe unto you) <hi>I will take you, and give you Paſtors according to my heart.</hi> How glorious is the exerciſe of mercy when this his faithfulnes takes hold of the Almighty? if his people provoke him, how is mercy exalted in the conflicts that are between juſtice and mercy? in the turning of divine bowels?<note place="margin"> Hoſ. 11.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ho.</hi> 11.8.9. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up</hi> Ephraim? <hi>how ſhall I deliver thee</hi> Iſrael? <hi>how ſhall I make thee as</hi> Admah? <hi>how ſhall I ſet thee as</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boim? <hi>mine heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together: I will not execute the fierceneſſe of mine anger, I will not return to deſtroy</hi> Ephraim, <hi>for I am God and not man, the holy One in the midſt of thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon ſhowes you why <hi>God waits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a provoking people</hi> and doth not cut them off in his Juſtice; [becauſe <hi>the Lord is a God of Judgement</hi>]</p>
            <p n="1"> 1. Some take <hi>Judgement</hi> for Juſtice here, and put the Emphaſis upon the word <hi>[God]</hi> the God of Judgment;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alvarez</hi> in locum.</note> 
               <hi>[Judicii Dominus]</hi> ſaith <hi>Alvarez,</hi> he may remit the puniſhment of ſinne without ſhowing a reaſon, and ſpare the guilty if he pleaſe without offence to any. <hi>Voluntas divina ſuprema lex,</hi> The Judg of all the earth cannot but do right; he is <hi>judicii Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, the God of Judgement;</hi> whereas if a man Judge ſhould acquit the guilty and let them paſſe unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113280:10"/> he ſhould ſinne againſt the Common-wealth, and violate his own duty; <hi>quia non eſt Judicii Dominus, ſed Domini vicarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2"> 2. Some take <hi>Judgement</hi> here for moderation, in puniſhing of ſinners in a way of oppoſition to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and wrath, as <hi>Ier.</hi> 10.24. <hi>O Lord correct me,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ier. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>but with Judgement, not in thine anger, leſt thou bring me to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> God therefore waiteth upon ſinners not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he is ſlow to anger, but alſo he moderates the execution of his Judgements; <hi>I will correct thee in meaſure, and will not leave thee altogether unpuniſhed</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Iacob, Jer.</hi> 30.11.<note place="margin"> Ier. 30.11.</note> that his people may not be conſumed under his correcting hand.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin"> Gods wiſdom to improve his waiting upon a ſinfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>3. Some take <hi>Judgement</hi> here for wiſdome or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall prudence and diſcretion in God, he waits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a provoking people ſometimes, becauſe he knowes when to apply mercy, and how to improve all opportunities to the beſt advantage of his owne glory, in his adminiſtrations to a ſinfull and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He can diſcerne when a people are fit for mercy, and diſtinguiſh between penitent and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners; the deceitfull heart, though it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperatly wicked ſhall not deceive him, but <hi>he will give to every man according to his waies. Jer.</hi> 17.9.10.<note place="margin"> Ier. 17.9.10.</note> Like a wiſe Phyſitian he knows when to purge, &amp; when to give cordials; ſo that, as in mercy he looketh for an opportunity that he may do good, ſo he knows how, to take it and when; and hence it is, that ſometimes he waits very long, till a people be brought into deſperate ſtraits, and out of all hopes ere he deliver them; becauſe the Church was not in tune for mercy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113280:11"/> till then he waits. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.8.9. <hi>The high waies lie waſt, the wayfaring man ceaſeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Iſa. 33.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>the earth mourneth,</hi> Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>is aſhamed, and hewen down:</hi> Sharon <hi>is like a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, &amp;c.</hi> and then will he be gracious, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>Now will I riſe, ſaith the Lord, now will I be exalted, now will I lift up my ſelf.</hi> And yet he is not like <hi>Carolus</hi> King of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who was ſurnamed <hi>Cunctator,</hi> becauſe he was wont to ſtay til opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was loſt; but rather like <hi>Fabius Cunctator,</hi> ſo called, becauſe he would alwaies ſtay till opportunity, and then would be ſure to take it.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, He waits, becauſe he knows how to take his times, &amp; ſeaſons to prevaile upon, and bring in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious people toward mercy, who yet are very far from, and unfit for it. A mans wiſdom ſhowes it ſelf much in diſcerning ſeaſons; The Lord ſpake unto <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> but he would not hear, and therefore he waites, becauſe he knew there would come an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity when <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> would hear, and hearken after the Lord,<note place="margin"> 2 Chro. 33.10.12.</note> in afflictions. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 33.10.12. and he waited not in vaine, for ſo it came to paſſe; <hi>when he was in afflictions he beſought the Lord his God, and humbled himſelf greatly before the God of his Fathers.</hi> So when the Lord had to do with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of their contumacy, that they were untracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>like a wild Aſſe in the Wilderneſſe, that ſnuffeth up the wind at her pleaſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ier. 2.24.</note> Ier. 2.24. <hi>In her occaſion who can turn her away?</hi> as good ſeek to take a hare with a Taber, (as we commonly ſay) yet the Lord knows how to meet with her, though for the preſent <hi>all that ſeek her, will not weary themſelves: in her moneth they ſhall find her,</hi> when this wild creature ſhall be great with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113280:11"/> young, not able thus to run about in the wilderneſſe, then a man may talke with her; ſo when <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath made up their iniquity, a full burden, and that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begins to take hold of them, then in their moneth God will find them: and as God knows his ſeaſons, ſo he knows by what means to prevaile, by Judgements or by mercies; ſome muſt be brought in by an earth-quake, others will be brought in as eaſily by a ſtill voice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He waits becauſe he is a God of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to know when the giving in of mercies will bring God moſt honour, and when Gods hand will be moſt clearly ſeen to give in mercies, ſo that they may be convincing mercies; thus he waited on his ſtiff-necked people, that he might be mercifull to them, even till <hi>Antiochus</hi> had broken all their power, ſo that there was no help to be expected; and then the Lord came in with <hi>Michaels</hi> deliverance, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.7. <hi>when he ſhall have accompliſhed to ſcatter the power of the holy people;</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Dan. 11.1.7.</note> for then they could ſee that their help was from God. Thus he waited upon the waſtful Prodigall till he had ſpent all, ſo that he muſt either have God or nothing, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. and then the Fathers imbraces are ſweet and welcome.<note place="margin"> Luk. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Before I come to the Uſe of the Prophets doctrine which the text preſents you, let us conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this age be not one of theſe [ſometimes] where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>God wonderfully ſuſpends his Judgments, and waites upon a provoking people; that he may be mercifull to them.</hi> Are we not aſtoniſhed and like unto them that dreame this day? while wee looke upon the <hi>God of our ſalvation anſwering us</hi> (as he doth) <hi>by terrible things
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113280:12"/> in his righteouſnes,</hi> doing terrible things that we look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not for, whereby the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines (even the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of enemies and oppoſition) do flow down and tremble at his preſence; he that hath formerly drawn out the ſword and bent his bow, and like an enemy fought againſt us, giving <hi>Iacob</hi> to the ſpoile and <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> to the robbers, has in the midſt of wrath remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred mercy; and when he ſaw that there was no man, and wondred that there was no interceſſor; his own Arme hath brought ſalvation to him, and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes it ſuſtained him. Who would have thought in a few months paſt, that we ſhould have ſeene ſuch a change in <hi>England,</hi> in ſo ſhort a time? that our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn faſts the faſt of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> monetle, and the faſt of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> month ſhould be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into ſolemne feaſts of joy and gladnes? that our thankſgiving dayes, ſhould over number our dayes of humiliation? Yet am I ſo farr from the opinion of laying aſide our humiliations, in theſe times of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, (as if they were inconſiſtent with our joyfull feaſts,) that I conceive the duties of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and rejoycing ſpiritually performed, very helpfull one to another, and to ſpiritualize one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; bleſſings obtained by prayer and faſting, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but affect the ſoul and raiſe it unto a greater pitch of ſpirituall thankfulneſſe; and when mercies have made the ſoule to rejoyce in God, it cannot but mourne over ſinne more ingenuouſly then before. If mercies will not work with a people this way, when God gives them in, after judgements, they will be, but <hi>lucida intervalla,</hi> preſages of greater Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to follow,<note place="margin"> Sim.</note> like the Sunſhine between two dread,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113280:12"/> full ſtormes; or rather like a reviving between two fits of a feaver, when the patient dyes of the latter: <hi>Chorazin</hi> that had been lift up to heaven by mercies, and the great works that were done in her, was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thruſt down to hell in Judgements. <hi>Ingentia beneficia, ingentia flagitia, ingentia ſupplicia,</hi> If great wickedneſſe follow great benefits, great puniſhments ſhall follow great wickedneſſe: as is confeſſed by <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9.13.14.<note place="margin"> Ezra. 9.13.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Repentance and reformation is the point that we muſt be brought unto, either by Judgments or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and ſince former Judgements have not brought us to it; O that the Lord would melt our hearts this day with his aſtoniſhing mercies! that our hard and frozen Spirits which would not be broken hitherto by the hammer of his Judgements, might now be ſoftened by the fire of his mercies! And truly (honorable and beloved) mercies (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they are given in to an undeſerving peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as our mercies are) are very proper premiſes and principles of godly ſorrow and ſhame for ſin, ſeeing that this is promiſed as a fruit of mercy.</p>
            <p>I have looked into the Book of God, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God hath been wont, in former times, to bring in his people to repentance and reformation, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances and mercies. For if God have never gone in ſuch a way with a people heretofore, I ſhould feare (that notwithſtanding our many and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full publick mercies wherewith God hath at preſent bleſſed our Land) we ſhould have an after-clap, and be brought back again into the refiners fire, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of affliction, that our droſſe (which is not yet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113280:13"/> ſevered from us) may be purged out, and our filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe depart from us, which is the way whereby God ordinarily prevailes with a people in that kind. And of all the hopefull preſidents I could find, wherein God hath brought in a people by mercy, this is the moſt eminent,<note place="margin"> Ezek. 36.31, 32. Applied.</note> 
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.31.32. <hi>Then ſhall yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your own evill wayes, and your doings that are not good, and ſhall loath your ſelves in your own ſight for your iniquities, and for your abominations. Not for your ſakes doe I this, ſaith the Lord God, be it known unto you, be aſhamed and confounded for your own wayes, O houſe of Iſrael.</hi> You may look upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this chapter, as <hi>Englands</hi> parallell in our preſent condition: They had defiled their own land with the bloud that they had ſhed, and with their Idols: yea, they had profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the name of God among the heathen alſo: and therefore the Lord had powred out his fury upon them,<note place="margin"> V. 17-21.</note> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 17.-21. but the Lord pitied them, for his own holy Name, which they had profaned, and he reſolved to ſanctifie his great and holy Name by delivering them from captivity, and ſetting them at peace in their own Land,<note place="margin"> V. 21-25.</note> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 21.-25. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he would reform them according to his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and make them a holy people, and their land which had been laid waſte, a fruitful land, <hi>v,</hi> 25-31.<note place="margin"> V. 25-31.</note> And when the Lord ſhall have done all this, and that without the leaſt deſert of theirs, (as the Lord bids them take notice of it, <hi>Be it known unto you</hi>) then ſhall they repent and be aſhamed. He is a ſtranger to <hi>England,</hi> that hath not ſeen <hi>England</hi> like unto <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> in their ſinnes, it hath been defiled with bloud
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113280:13"/> and idols, whereby the Name of our God hath been profaned; and like to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their puniſhments, the Lord hath powred out his fury upon them; and like unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their deliverances and mercies, God is now ſanctifying his holy Name, which we had pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, by delivering us, and making way to ſettle us at peace in our own land. The Lord make <hi>England</hi> like unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their repentance and reformation alſo. Now becauſe the undeſervedneſſe of mercie, (and that they are given to thoſe that could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect them) has a great influence upon the heart, as appears in that God preſſeth it ſo often, <hi>v.</hi> 21.22. &amp; 32. I deſire to ſet before your judicious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, three things,<note place="margin"> How to mourn in the ſight of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mercies. Directions.</note> that may help us to a mourning frame of ſpirit in the ſight of our great mercies, that we may <hi>loath our ſelves in our own ſight</hi> this day <hi>for our iniquities, and be confounded for our own wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Let us ſet our ſins this day, (at leaſt ſome of them) in the ſight of our hearts together, with our mercies; <hi>David</hi> looks upon both together, while from his mercies he reflects upon himſelf, when his people offered ſo willingly toward build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Temple, 1 <hi>Cro.</hi> 29.14. <hi>Who am I? and what is my people?</hi> So wee while we look upon the mercies that God hath heaped on us, may ſit down aſtoniſhed, &amp; ſay, Who are we, and what is our people? are we not an <hi>Apoſtatizing</hi> nation? we werefallen from our Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive reformation, &amp; there is yet a ſpirit of whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the midſt of us to oppoſe reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this day. Let us look upon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> how ſeverely the Lord dealt with her for abuſing his love, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning aſide to ſpirituall fornication as we have done.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113280:14"/>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.38.40.<note place="margin"> Ezek 13.36.40.</note> 
               <hi>I will judge thee</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>as women that break wedlock and ſhed bloud are judged; and I will give thee bloud in fury and jealouſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are alſo a Covenant-breaking people, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken the name of God in vaine, how ſhould the Lord hold us guiltleſſe? this brought wrath upon <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> unavoidably; the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> have broken my Covenant,<note place="margin"> Iſa. 11.11.</note> 
               <hi>Ier.</hi> 11.11. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will bring evill upon them, which they ſhall not be able to eſcape.</hi> We have been and are apt to ſay a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, to ſuch as God would not have us ſay a Confederacy to; and to cover with a covering, but not of Gods Spirit, as our Prophet complains, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.1. we ſubject Religion, and the things of God,<note place="margin"> Iſa. 30 1.</note> to carnall ends, being led by carnall policie, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of conſcience and higheſt concernment, too much verifying in that of old; <hi>Mater peperit filiam, et filia devoravit matrem;</hi> Policy hath alwaies been a clog to Religion, and would never ſuffer former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to adventure upon a through reformation; the Lord keep our generation that we daſh not againſt the ſame rock!</p>
            <p>Though the Lord hath pronounced them <hi>curſed that truſt in man,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ier. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>and make fleſh their arme,</hi> Ier. 17.5. we are full of carnall confidence, lifted up, or caſt down, according as outward means and humane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities, do ebb or flow; like <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we ſeek God when we need him,<note place="margin"> Pſa. 78.</note> in a low condition, and when we are delivered we forget him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.</p>
            <p>We are guilty of ſelf-ſeeking, every man looks for his gaine from his quarter, (as <hi>Paul</hi> complained) all men ſeek their own, none the things of Jeſus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113280:14"/> Chriſt: To be acted by a private Spirit in publike undertakings, doth not only blemiſh the beauty, but alters the nature of the undertaking, and makes that ſinfull, which if acted with a publique Spirit, had been commendable and glorious.<note place="margin"> 2 King. 10.30.</note> 
               <hi>Jehu</hi> in cuting off the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> did according to the word of the Lord; but becauſe he had ends of his own in doing it,<note place="margin"> Hoſ. 1.4.</note> the bloud of <hi>Ahab</hi> is put upon his account.</p>
            <p>We ſuffer Gods Houſe to lye waſt while we dwell in ſeiled houſes; by diviſion and errors, truth is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in the ſtreet and confuſion haſteth, and yet we look on and lay it not to heart.</p>
            <p>We turn head againſt Jeſus Chriſt, like thoſe that break his bands and caſt away his cords from them;<note place="margin"> Pſa. 1.</note> we refuſe his eaſie yoke, and caſt off his light burden: as if we were of their mind that ſaid, <hi>wee will not have this man rule over us. Luc.</hi> 19.21.<note place="margin"> Luc. 19.21.</note> All this ſcumme is in the midſt of us untaken away, and all this droſſe and much more is in us in the very fire of Gods Judgements, ſo that in our filthineſſe is lewdneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now conſider Gods uſuall manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſuch ſinners; <hi>He will ſet his face againſt them, and they ſhall be ſlain before their enemies, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Lev. 26.17.</note> Lev. 26.17. and if they walke contrary, he will puniſh them ſeaven times more, and ſeaven times more, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times more for their ſinnes; and at laſt walke contrary unto them in fury. The like alſo when <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> grew incorrigable (as <hi>England</hi> hath been) and would not return to the Lord; what gradations of Judgment are muſtered up againſt them?<note place="margin"> Amos 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, Conſider Gods admirable patience towards us above his former dear people; he bare with their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113280:15"/> maners in the wildernes 40 years, but whats that to fourſcore years patience wherein he hath born with <hi>England?</hi> and all theſe yeares, what pride, and contempt, what abominations hath God put up at the hands of a fooliſh Nation? And is not <hi>England</hi> yet deſtroyed? She hath boyled in <hi>Sodoms</hi> luſt, but ſhe is not conſumed with <hi>Sodoms</hi> fire: ſhe hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Iſraels</hi> iniquities, but ſhe hath not ſuffered <hi>Iſraels</hi> puniſhments. God did exalt his mercy in ſparing the rebellions of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ezek, 20.14.17.22.</note> 
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.14.17.22. when it was breaking forth againſt them three times, yet ſtill he wrought for his own names ſake; but how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hee hath reſtrained his wrath when it was ready to break out againſt <hi>England,</hi> and wrought for his own names ſake, to ſpare us, in turning his wrath away, I appeal unto you. In all this, if we conſider how God hath out-gone, I ſay not our deſert, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our faith, our prayers, and expectations in the greatneſſe &amp; multitude of his bleſſings, giving them in moſt ſeaſonably, when we were upon the brink of ruine, by his own hand, ſo that we may ſay, <hi>If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, we had been ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up.</hi> And that he ſhould doe all theſe after ſo much patience, wherein he hath many a time turned his wrath away, notwithſtanding our many and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking ſinnes, wherewith we have preſſed the Lord as a Cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaves, ſo that he hath groaned under us, (as it were) and complained of our unkindneſſe,<note place="margin"> Micah 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>O my people! what have I done unto thee, and wherein have I wearied thee? Teſtifie againſt me.</hi> What hard heart can yet tread upon ſuch bowels? Whoſe eyes would not run over in looking upon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113280:15"/> thoſe divine meltings? and ſay, It is known unto us this day, that not for our ſakes, but for his own holy names ſake which we had polluted, the Lord hath done all this: we are aſhamed and confounded for our own wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note>] The uſe which our Prophet makes of his own Doctrine, is, of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to a duty, <hi>Wayt upon the Lord,</hi> backed with the encouragement of a promiſe; <hi>Bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi> He that of meer goodneſſe turnes away his diſpleaſure from a people while they do ſinne againſt him, and waits upon them for an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to doe them good, will much more not diſappoint them when they wait for him: if he wait in mercy, 'tis fit they ſhould wait in duty:<note place="margin"> Waiting for God, what it is.</note> if he wait to give, and they wait to receive, mercy, the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion cannot but be bleſſed. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The duty exhorted to, is to wait, and waiting is to return from ſinne, to a diligent attendance upon God in the wayes of obedience, joyned with a fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and patient expectation of ſalvation and mercy according to his will.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum"> It conſiſteth ſn 4 things. 1.</note>It is made up of foure ingredients, 1. of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſinning is contrary to waiting, and therefore there muſt firſt be a turning, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Turn thou to thy God,</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>Ephraim</hi>) <hi>keep mercy and judgment,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Hoſea 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>and wait on thy God continually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 There muſt be a diligent attendance upon God, with a heedfull obſervance of his wayes, ſuch as the Church profeſſeth, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 123.2:<note place="margin"> Pſal. 123.2.</note> 
               <hi>As the eyes of ſervants look unto the hand of their maſters, and as the eyes of a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113280:16"/> maiden to the hand of her miſtreſſe, ſo our eyes wait upon the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3 It muſt be in the wayes of obedience: waiting is not an idle poſture, but imports the diligence of a Sentinell: if we wait for ſalvation and deliverance, there muſt be activity and diligence to ſerve Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence for <hi>Sions</hi> enlargement, the Lord expecteth <hi>help againſt the mighty,</hi> though he needs it not.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4 There had need to bee Faith (with her two daughters, Hope and Patience) to make up and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on this bleſſed work of waiting for God: we muſt wait as <hi>the Husband-man for the pretious fruits of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Ja. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Ia.</hi> 5.7. There muſt be a ſpace between ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reaping time: if we ſow in teares, expect to reap in joy. <hi>The Iſles ſhall wait upon me, and in mine arme ſhall they truſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Iſa. 51.5.</note> ſaith God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.5. Wee muſt not truſt in our Bow or Sword: creature confidence cannot ſtand with a right waiting upon God. <hi>'Tis thou that ſaveſt us from our enemies, Pſal.</hi> 44. And where our waiting is, there is our hope. <hi>What wait I for?</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Pſal. 39.7.</note> ſaith <hi>David, my hope is in thee, Pſal.</hi> 39.7. And where hope is,<note place="margin"> Rom. 8.25.</note> there is patience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>If wee hope for that we ſee not, then doe with patience wait for it.</hi> And ſo we are required, <hi>Reſt in the Lord and wait pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently for him,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Pſal. 37.7.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalm</hi> 37.7. How ever the Lord pleaſe to diſpoſe of things till his promiſe be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be content, and <hi>reſt</hi> in his work, and wait for his promiſe. The Churches eſtate is couched in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and moſt in reverſion, and therefore will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to be waited for,<note place="margin"> Heb. 10.36.</note> and that with patience. <hi>Yee have need of patience, that after yee have done the will of God, yee may receive the promiſe,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113280:16"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin"> They that wait for God ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed 4 wayes. Heb. 10.36.</note>The motive whereby he drives on to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty, is the bleſſing that attends it, <hi>Bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. They ſhall be enabled by the Lords everlaſting ſtrength, to goe on without fainting through all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and difficulties, in the way of their hopes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. <hi>They that wait upon the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Iſa. 40.31.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walk and not faint.</hi> It is a ſeaſonable incouragement unto you (honorable &amp; beloved) to wait upon God, that he may carry you through the weighty affaires, of Church and State, that will require renewed ſtrength.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. They ſhall be bleſſed with comfort and peace in their owne ſoules for the preſent, though their hopes ſhould be deferred, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3.<note place="margin"> Iſa. 26.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whoſe mind is ſtaied on thee.</hi> There's a ſweetneſſe in the very duty of waiting on God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Their hopes ſhall be accompliſhed, they ſhall ſee the fruit of their waiting, as appeares by <hi>Davids experience, Pſal.</hi> 40.1, 2, 3.<note place="margin"> Pſal. 40.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>I waited patiently for the Lord, and hee inclined unto me and heard my cry, hee brought me up out of a horrible pit, and he hath put a new ſong in my mouth, even praiſe unto our God.</hi> They ſhall never be aſhamed, but ſhall ſay as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9.<note place="margin"> Iſa. 25.9.</note> 
               <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him,</hi> by our multiplied mercies in the ſucceſſe of our Armies, God hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a doore of hope for us in the valley of <hi>Achor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. They ſhall be bleſſed everlaſtingly; though they ſhould never live to ſee the accompliſhment of Gods promiſes of temporall ſalvation, which they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113280:17"/> wait for, yet they ſhall have a day wherein they ſhall receive the waiting ſervants bleſſing of entring into the joy of their Lord, and ſhall ſay by experience, <hi>Bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
